{
  "reference_number": "1509",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "A set target in legislation was recommended as point 6.1 in the previous Parliamentary Commissioner report - July 2017 and is\n mentioned in the new Parliamentary Commissioner's report - March 2018 and is something I highly support. A set target provides not\n only provides a clear signal to the business community but will provide a competitive advantage to NZ firms as first movers as the\n\n world moves towards a low carbon economy. Setting targets later may well lead to political interference and a weakening of any\n targets along with more uncertainty."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Long-Lived Gases and Stabilised Short-Lived Gases - Long-lived gases to net zero by 2050 while also stabilising short-lived gases",
      "answer_index": 12,
      "notes": "A recent peer reviewed published paper highlighted the differences between using “CO2-equivalent” and using a metric known as\n “global warming potential” (GWP). (links below). This paper clearly shows that using CO2e over representatives short term gases like\n methane. As such the second option is a more accurate and fair measure of NZ's impact on climate change. A solution to the\n\n misrepresentations of CO2-equivalent emissions of short-lived climate pollutants under ambitious mitigation: npj Climate and\n Atmospheric Science volume 1, Article number: 16 (2018) https://www.nature.com/articles/s41612-018-0026-8\n https://www.carbonbrief.org/guest-post-a-new-way-to-assess-global-warming-potential-of-short-lived-pollutants"
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "I firmly believe that NZ can meet all it's reduction requirement domestically and having access to international carbon units is likely to\n\n offer an excuse for future politicians to reduce required changes here in our own county, which will lead to NZ not moving down the\n path towards a low carbon economy quickly enough which is not only bad for global emissions but also would mean that NZ would\n\n not be a first mover and thus reduce any competitive advantage."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "For business certainty it is important that the target cannot be revised, allowing the target to change will let future politicians take the\n easy way out instead of making the required changes to transition NZ towards a successful low carbon economy"
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "I agree with the new parliamentary commissioner reported 'A Zero Carbon Act for NZ' (March 2018) that the emission budgets should\n be every 6 years to match NZ's electoral cycle with 3 year interim updates. This will let each Government respond to the budgets\n within their time in Government and I’m sure that NZ will still be able to meet international 5 yearly reporting requirements using the\n\n latest budget or interim update. Tying in to our electoral cycle is a great benefit for future Governments with less confusion here in\n NZ."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "Business, and NZ as a whole need a constant environment in which to act and to respond to, and by having potential changing\n\nemission budgets, even 10 years out in the 3rd budget just creates uncertainty in the economy plus the planet is warming so quickly\nthat all needs to be done to reduce our emissions. Potentially there could be a qualifier that the third budget could be modified under\n\npredetermined exceptional circumstances."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "As above for point 6. Business, and NZ as a whole need a constant environment in which to act and to respond to, and by having\n\npotential changing emission budgets, even 5 years out in the 2nd budget just creates uncertainty in the economy plus the planet is\nwarming so quickly that all needs to be done to reduce our emissions."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I strongly support annual reports on tracking towards the emissions budget, this should be done by the climate commission. I also\n\nstrongly support aligning emissions budgets within the ETS, as the ETS is the main GHG emission tool within NZ so this makes good\nsense."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes I strongly support time-frames to achieve emissions budgets"
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "There is no mention in the discussion document on engaging with the 18 to 30 year old youth of NZ. As such I recommend that\nthere is a mechanism setup to work with the next generation including with school leavers, these are the people who will be living\n\nwith our decisions long term and as those who have the most at stake, and they are also those most likely to be not involved in the\nsetting of any plans to meet the budgets. I also recommend there is engagement with Chartered Environmentalist’s in NZ; through\nIEMA (The UK’s sustainability professional network with 15,000 members). There are a number of IEMA members now living in NZ,\n\nand there is an IEMA-NZ chapter; these are highly qualified experts in the area of sustainability and GHG emissions."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I strongly support that the climate chance commission advises on the progress towards NZ climate reduction target on an annual\nprogress report. I also strongly support the recommendation made by the previous Parliamentary Commissioner (stepping stones to\n\nParis & Beyond) July 2017; that Climate Change Minister must give reasons why any climate change commission advice is not\nfollowed."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": "I strongly support the climate change commission making decisions on the number of units available in the NZ ETS; yes this will have\nan impact on the NZ economy and society in general but is no different that the decisions made by the Reserve Bank which impact\n\non our economy. The Government sets the budgets (like our inflation target) and the Climate Change Commission set the ETS units\nin response (same as the Reserve Bank sets the Official Cash Rate). The Climate Change Commission can be setup to include the\nrequired external experts who can set the number of units in the ETS separate from the Government, this would give NZ a very\n\nrobust independent ground breaking response to reducing GHG emissions and would be a key driver towards moving NZ towards a\nlow carbon economy, which will transform NZ into a more successful and wealthier country in the long run."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I would also recommend that a youth representative is included - as a member of the next generation and those who will be most\n\nimpacted by global warming. ."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Both the new and previous parliamentary commissioner’s recommended that adaption with a national level risk assessment and a\nnational adaption strategy are included in the Zero Carbon Bill, and I strongly support this position. Otherwise local authority’s will\n\nrespond in an ad-hoc manner which will create uncertainty and will likely leave late responses to some climate change risks which will\nbe more costly to deal with. Any administrative and compliance costs will be more than offset by the savings from early responses to\n\nclimate change risks."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "We need to not only reduce our GHG emissions but NZ needs to ensure we adapt to the changes which will negatively impact on us\n\nand our environment, as such I strongly support the proposed functions,"
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "A simple golden rule is that you can’t manage what you don’t manage, and regular adaptation reporting is key to ensure we know is\nworking and what is not working. The administrative and compliance costs are minor compared to the extra costs from actions which\nare not working or climate change risks which are not be addressed – which the reporting will identify. In short regular adaption\n\nreporting will actually save us money in the long run as well as helping to ensure NZ responds to the climate change risks happening\naround us."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I strongly support a Zero Carbon Bill that has targets and an adaption strategy and I really hope that their is cross party support for\nthis bill"
    }
  ]
}
